welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
all right check-ins
whoof I feel like this like a delicious
do mosts is flowing through my body and
if you don't know what the word Dumas is
it's probably for the best right now
welcome to the store fighting this Peter
Lindbergh
I'm the Stewart of the stoah and a Stowe
is a place for us to cohere and dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of this moment and today we have
dug a Tartar and I think I'm pronouncing
that correctly
dr. Turing who is I'm good on media so
you can correct me yeah - Taryn - Taryn
data again today there's no R in the
first ta that we are from the Tarte ours
but we've given that part up or just
okay and then Doug is he's the creator
or something called the bio motive
framework and a lot of people a lot of
my friends here in Toronto the
sense-making community they're just
raving about this framework and then
Doug came to Toronto and I told months
ago and I missed that one and everyone
was like it's like the soft squad
emerged from it and I'm like wish I
was there but I'm grateful that Doug has
decided to visit the stoah and I'm going
to be I'm pretty green at this so I'm
gonna get an introduction I'm sure a lot
of you are gonna get an introduction as
well so what we're gonna do we're going
to record the first part that was going
to give like a talk about 20 men talk
introducing the modality and then we're
going to do an exercise and then I'll
stop the record button when we go into
the exercise so that being said I will
hand it over to you Doug and you're a
mute again I'm see if i unmuted you
so I welcome everybody this is exciting
for me I'm always interested in exposing
new people to this way of seeing the
world and what's particularly
interesting is that I'm coming to a
forum that has a particular way of
seeing the world and I'm kind of curious
to see if there's any clashes or if this
is a complementary kind of approach just
being stoic and being you know embracing
stoicism and part partly because I kind
of AB lived these things I know what the
important points are but it really helps
me to know kind of who my audience is so
what I'd like if you don't mind before I
start riffing in a particular direction
is if I can get like three or four
people to give me like a thirty second
to a minute
kind of what it what brought you here
and what are you hoping to get from this
if you can just give me some idea of
what's going on inside your mind in your
worlds and I'll assume that three to
five people is a representative sample
not that it really is but it'll give me
something to kind of resonate with so if
if we want to put up you guys know how
to put up your hands you can raise your
hand if you open up the participants
window and if you do that I should get a
list of people popping up to the top so
if you don't mind sharing with me and
the group what brings you here and what
you're hoping to get from it I'd
appreciate it so while people are
considering that and the other thing is
we're going to record this first part
and then when it comes to the exercise
where we might get into some
experiential sharing we're gonna make
sure that that's not available to the
public okay so you can you can share
here I imagine this isn't going to be
too revealing in this first part we're
gonna record my talk and then when it
comes to the exercise we're gonna either
stop recording it or just reassure you
that we will not be distributing it
anywhere okay does everyone agree with
that it's all good and comfort and great
see a lot of nodding heads
Supt is good too so Jonathan if you
don't mind sharing what you've heard and
what you're hoping to get from this that
would be wonderful
Hey so I'm actually decently familiar
with your work mostly from friends have
been more directly involved like
tattooed somewhere on the originator
Sauron originator and and I've kind of
done like prototypical attempts at doing
this work on my own I mean each time I
go to something you hold I seem to get
like another piece of the puzzle for my
own thing so it's been valuable in that
sense I'm trying to move through some
feelings right now and use all the help
I can get that sort of thing awesome
well thank you Jonathan and and I taught
you in Malcolm
we're both he goes my Malcolm ocean I
didn't know if that's his real last name
but but they were both instrumental in
starting the solid squad and I actually
have some sob squad towels that I'm
gonna start sending out to people I do
life coaching with because I find that
when we do this work they just go
through too many Kleenexes and so towels
kind of work when you're first doing the
clearing stuff part of the assumption
that we'll talk about is that crying is
good for you and a missing piece of our
health right now but you got to do it
properly or otherwise it's not that
useful so thank you Jonathan and Peter
can you make me a co-host so that I can
lower their hands after they've spoken
and I can just keep track and I need
more volunteers I've only got one more
after Jonathan so if we can get you know
another volunteer or two I would
appreciate it
Thanks so so Andrew if you can share
sure I I heard about you through the
stoah or more specifically through AJ
and he spoke very highly and I feel like
because of the you know just being
isolated they're not isolated but kind
of like being in this like you know I
guess physically isolated in the
coronavirus like there's a lot of Tears
that are happening so I'm really wanna
like and a lot of embracing of a
feelings so I wanna like really kind of
just own it like I really want to like
you know kind of sharpen my my feeling
toolbox sweet and and I'll say that you
know there I don't mean to be from my
experience you know I've come to
appreciate that there are productive and
healthy ways of crying and processing
your feelings and there are unhealthy
ways of crying and processing your
feelings and what I'm gonna offer you is
a method that seems to be healthy I'm
not willing to say this is the truth I
just know that this is a very useful
heuristic okay and and I'll explain how
I got the nine core feelings after
they're actually research-based but
there's still it still new this is an
emerging framework but I I have just
really come to appreciate the potency of
seeing the emotional world through this
lens and how it can make such a
difference in our both physical while
our mental and our physical health and
our social health so and in my own
practice once Corona started probably
increased by 50% and and I'm sure it's
because all the people have been putting
off who knew about the work and been
putting off it's like this isn't the
right time it's like it was just in
their face it's like I can't avoid this
anymore and I've had some really
wonderful
you know people doing some very intense
work
and getting the benefits from it so this
is a wonderful opportunity to do the
introspective work and this is a really
wonderful tool to to do it with so
hopefully by the end of the session you
guys will also be agreeing with me so
thanks for sharing Andrew and thank you
Raven if you could share yeah hi hi Doug
thanks for being here um so how did I
hear about this I'm really naive to this
process I don't really know much not
much about it but I have a friend who
went to the monastic Academy for their
pre-apprenticeship program and he
specifically told me that the bio
emotive workshops for him were really
catalyzed thing of like emotional growth
and change and that he thought I
specifically would be able to work
through things using this method I and
like you know I have a hearsay because
he told me what he experienced and now I
have a fuzzy kind of recollection of
what he said but I think I'm really
intellectual and so I intellectualize my
emotional states and I feel like in some
ways I've just reached an endpoint of
being able to actually process what's
going on and in an anterior way and so I
think I'm interested in new ways of
accessing my inner world and it seems
like this this method has that potential
to it so that's why I'm here today
sweet well I I'm glad to be able to
introduce it to you firsthand like this
in person I'm looking forward to
people's reactions so as anybody not
been exposed to somebody who's done this
work and could you tell me what drew you
in
just anyone else willing to chat
otherwise I'll give up if no one says
yes in a in a second Victoria wonderful
I don't have my a video on right now but
um I'm afraid I didn't Vancouver so I'm
joining you from the west coast and a
friend of mine Michelle let Nick she's a
Winnipeg person and you know that you
the smile says it all
she we've she's a really good friend of
mine and we have lots of very
existential conversations all the time
and we had one this week and she just
threw this at me out of the blue and was
like you need to do this this is the
right thing for you research she she
sent me some links and the grades that
she's part of we have an exam sure I
think Ally so yeah so I've absolutely no
idea what I'm getting into
I don't know anything about this at all
by trust Michelle's show implicitly and
her sort of guidance on it and I'm it
just it felt like a bit of a
serendipitous callin or whatever so I'm
here as a complete novice as well like
Raven said so just to kind of see what
see what this is all about and you just
felt it felt like a right time this
obviously with everything that we've
been experiencing personally and
collectively it's it does feel like the
time for this kind of work so so yeah
I'm just I'm here with perfect faith
really good you see what happens
alright well it's probably good to have
faith in Michele she's a wonderful
person she's credible being and becoming
quite a glowing being as well oh yeah
I'm gonna stop it here I appreciate Jane
putting up her hand but I'm I'm I know
we've got a lot to cover and so I'm
gonna start talking and one of the first
things that and and I I don't know Peter
yeah you're letting people in because
I've let some people into there
a concept that I want to introduce you
to most of you haven't heard of this
word and if you have it's usually in an
individual context but I when I first
started getting into clinical work I
really I done work in an area called
culture or called alexithymia and Alexa
findings were something that you could
actually in interesting the concept came
out of Toronto by a researcher I think
his name was Taylor and he measured
people's ability to to process their
emotions and he had a scale and on that
scale if you took it about 15% of people
would be considered alexa thymic so it
was a toronto alexithymia scale the TAS
and I used that for quite a number of
years but as a researcher when I
actually went into clinical work and I
was working with people trying to get
them do I was using a again ones
focusing technique but I was really
helping people get to the tears it was
really clear that when I asked the
question to people what are you feeling
they couldn't answer it they were giving
me stories about it they'd stayed while
I feel and then they'd give me a story
and they'd give me behavioral analogues
or metaphors but almost nobody talked
about their feelings and so I I come up
with this concept of cultural
alexithymia and it basically means
there's a problem somewhere in either
experiencing or expressing or resolving
your emotional state
okay so alexithymia where we as a
researcher would think 10 to 15 percent
of the population has alexithymia or
some trouble with you know processing
their emotions my experience as a
clinician was it was more like 85 90 95
percent of people were deficit in that
area and there is an interesting thing
that for for more theoretical context I
use the concept
the triune brain as a good metaphor for
the kind of different ways of
approaching the world so Paul MacLean
was a brilliant researcher that in the
70s came up with this triune brain
concept and more and more researchers
are embracing it there we know that the
brain is modular exactly what the
modules are everybody argues about but
the bigger set of picture the bigger
picture is that we've got a physical
brain an emotional brain and an
intellectual brain now they're all
highly interconnected but in terms of
modules we seem to have these three
independent networks that are looking at
the world through a different lens and
so he called them the reptilian the
mammalian and the Neo mammalian and some
other you know words but basically it
comes down to and this was based on like
30 years of research right and
neuroanatomical maps and studying
animals fur like in their brain
structures but it comes down to we have
a physical brain that looks after our
body and then on top of that which is
the reptilian brain so it regulates
heart rate and digestion and you know
basic survival stuff we've got an a
limbic brain or an emotional brain that
looks after what I refer to as our
relational dynamics okay and that's
where mammals come in that fight flight
dominance hierarchy starts to organize
animals into groups so that a pack of
wolves can bring down a caribou that an
individual animal can't and it's the
hierarchy that comes from the anger
fight component and the submission that
organizes that activity and then once
you've got the group's there's bonding
and everything so you get both the
social and survival and social emotions
there and that basically is a
rudimentary form of communication it
allows groups to form and communicate
and work together and that's mammals
pretty much all mammals that's why we
can bond with dogs because they have
that emotional ring and it's hard to
bond in the same way with the reptile
and if you feel really bonded to a
reptile that's wonderful but I'm not
sure the reptile feels bonded to you
because they don't have the structures
that allow that kind of processing to
take place there may be some exceptions
but in general mammals have a very
specific bonding and group relational
kind of status that they're always
processing and then the intellectual
brain which is characteristics of
primates formed and allowed us to think
about the world the other ones are just
very much being in the world and this
trichotomy actually kind of gets
rediscovered and formed into different
ways of seeing the world every ten or
fifteen or a hundred years so when I
went to school we informally talked
about the Nerds
you know the academics the jocks and the
artsy types and that corresponds to the
physical brain dominant ones the
emotionally dominant ones and the
intellectually dominant ones even though
I didn't say in that order and we see
that in Buddhism we've got body speech
and mind which corresponds to the
physical the the speech when it's done
right is an emotional expressive kind of
process and the mind is the intellect
and and we see these ways of seeing the
world I've got a blog where I talk about
another five or ten different ways of
how this triune structure of our human
condition shows up in our world in
different ways and our culture is
extremely biased towards nurturing the
physical so we got strong athletes and
surgeons right and we nurture the
intellect with all of our years of echod
academic training but the emotional
system gets very little explicit
training
if you know the best we do is we
encourage the arts you know and and
dance and expression nowadays and you
know modern art is it modern dance is
very expressive but we don't really
understand the emotional system to the
level that we understand the other two
systems now I make an explanation
because I was very confused by why if
we've evolved through the physical
emotional and intellectual brains and
we're all into this intellect why don't
we have a better understanding of the
emotional brain if this is something
we've already bought through and this is
where I really was excited to come up
with well I've spent a lot of time in
integral my my wife Darlene who is on
this call I saw her smiling and I just
see her picture there we taught integral
theory we got involved with it in the
90s and we taught integral theory to a
group in Selkirk for a vote in her nine
years and part of integral theory is
this embrace of evolutionary development
that human beings go through stages of
development and what in a theory that I
put together that's a slight variation
of acqua integral I call it Eva Kor
evolving brains and quadrants and I
presented this in 2010 at a conference
for integral theory the basic tenet is
that our developmental stages kind of go
through the physical brain the emotional
brain and the intellectual brain and
that the traditional or the how many
people are familiar with in integral and
spiral dynamics if you can just raise
your hands yeah most people are a lot of
people are which is wonderful
so the the basic gist is that we know
that the blue stage of development which
I refer to is traditional
really it's about rules and roles and so
I grew up in the 50s 60s and I caught
the end of the 50s which was very
traditional in terms of how our
households were structured and how we
treated women and children and you know
I would hear things like kids should be
seen and not heard you know the man is
the king of his man's home is his castle
women should be barefoot pregnant and in
the kitchen and we were kind of appalled
at some of these things now we don't
follow these but these aphorisms were
ways of training people into their roles
right like as a kid you were just told
kids should be seen and not heard so I'm
being told what my role is women are
told what their role is and that
structure of development works because
everyone plays their role but if you
start introducing emotions to that like
do you get to be depressed and make the
meals for your husband you can't because
if you don't make your meals husband
doesn't eat husband doesn't go out to
the farm and work you know or on the
field or whatever he's doing everything
falls apart
if the man gets depressed and can't work
can't fulfill his role it falls apart so
for the most part emotions were
extremely suppressed and how many people
are if you're old enough to have heard
the phrase you want something to cry you
know you're gonna cry I'll give you
something to cry about
put up your hand like and and what's
amazing is like how many of you aren't
from North America I've had people in
Sweden put up their hand and Europe put
up man I go how the hell does a mean
like that spread around the entire world
without anybody being conscious of it
but it's there across all the cultures
you're gonna cry oh give you something
to cry about and I was literally spanked
until I stopped crying that's when I
would stop getting spanked
I was literally taught I had to suppress
my emotions to survive
so that was traditional we then moved
into orange modern individuality and
emotions just get in the way of your
achievement they interfere with your
ability to a function so you suppress
them plus you know you're in an
individual mode so emotions don't really
have a role it's not till we get to
post-modernism that suddenly we care
about having a deep relationship with
people so how many people here are
looking for or in a relationship where
they want a deep soulful connection with
their partner
now almost everybody's putting up their
hand if you would have asked that
question in the 50s and 60s people would
have said what the hell are you talking
about that's not what it's about it's
like that man makes enough money
he's got good teeth and a healthy body
you know he'll be a good person to have
offspring with and and that's why
arranged marriages work in that rhythm
that level of development because you're
looking for a role the individual
doesn't matter so we've moved into a
postmodern context where we want
individual we want to be individuals and
we want to know the other individual and
what's the best question to ask somebody
if you want to know about their soul if
you want to know about the depths of who
they are well how do you feel about that
right what's going on with the all the
protests in North America you want to
really get to know someone you say how
do you feel about the protests whereas
in traditional it would be you know
those people out there they shouldn't be
doing that that's wrong they're
disrupting society right there's just
really one or two answers and it's
pretty black-and-white but here if I
asked each individual here how do you
feel about the protests I would get very
different answers and it would be an
opportunity for me to get to know you
deeply especially if I shared Wow like
that's very different than how I feel it
it almost is disruptive to hear you say
that and I'm curious as to how you got
there
that's a very postmodern perspective and
how many people have done circling
and you recognize the kind of tone that
I portrayed in in that curiosity
non-judgmental curiosity that's about
the depth of connection without judging
the other person's perspectives because
you want to try on that world as a
clinician I've learned that no matter
how quote crazy somebody appears in
their actions if I can look out their
eyes their world starts to make sense if
I can ask the right questions on how you
see this and what you're feeling
suddenly their configuration forms and
it's like wow now I understand why you
wanted to X or why or why you did that
it seemed crazy at first but I can see
how it makes sense to you so it's that
deep feeling exchange that we're now all
primed for but don't have the tools for
because if I ask you how you feel about
X or Y I can almost guarantee most of
you not give me feelings you'll give me
stories or metaphors or beliefs and some
of you who give feelings that's awesome
you're you're not Alexa thymic you know
but the the just kind of note that when
you ask people what they're feeling see
if they actually give you feelings I was
listening in on an expressive therapy
call the other day and someone said how
do you feel about that and I and nobody
nobody actually gave a feeling they all
just started talking it's like I feel
that these people really don't
understand what's going on it's like
well that's not a feeling right and then
you might not even recognize that that's
not a feeling but we'll get to that
after so I'm gonna pause here for a
moment I've covered a lot of ground and
I'll take some questions and then we'll
move on to the next little phase so then
you want to have any questions that they
want to clarify just pop your hand up
and then we'll we'll clarify that okay
I've covered a lot of ground and I just
wanna and if you don't have a question
that at least
maybe give me some feedback as to
whether this is making sense or if this
is if there's any insights or if this is
helping you in any way engine if you can
speak thanks Doug
I was understanding you correctly
there's a historical mark to us
suppressing emotions and he seems to
have suggested that the lifestyle and
livelihood of a farmer particularly
causes emotion suppression did I
understand it correctly and could you
explain why the farming lifestyle
particularly encouraged just that more
than what kingly and and I'll say it's
not the farming lifestyle so I'm glad
you're asking for clarification and this
is where this is actually the joy of
post-modernism is that people will ask
questions for clarification and you have
an opportunity because people had live
in such different worlds right like in
my world what I said was just it made
sense now you're hearing it differently
and so I get a chance to you know
explain the nuances so in North America
Canada in the 1950s and earlier probably
80 90 percent of families even in cities
were one generation removed from the
farm that most people had the if you
said I'm going to the farm for the
weekend people knew what you meant
because they had a grandpa or a granny
still living on the farm and there was
an era where that so that was confounded
with the developmental 1950s 40s 50s 60s
of traditional consciousness and so you
can be on a farm now on a commune and
you got a postmodern embrace of farming
but back then they were very merged that
the farming kind of mentality the
pioneer mentality was very traditional
when we landed in North America it was a
very traditional consciousness it's
still part of colonialism and so
for me those two are synonymous but it's
no longer true anymore does that is that
making sense to you maybe then I would
follow up like could you elaborate on
why emotional suppression is like
adaptive and helpful under those
circumstances because in traditional
consciousness your obligation is to
fulfill your role if you're a husband or
a worker you just have to do what your
ex what you're expected to do and
emotions get in the way of that
and you and and emotions are two
individualizing right they start making
you unique and so like when the when the
hippies came into being and they grew
hair long that was a radical symbol of
protest against the conformity of the
roles that they were expected to step
into right so that was their rebellion
against conforming to the roles I I
literally watched my father yell at my
mother for saying she wanted to get a
driver's license why do you need to
leave the house what are you going to do
I can take you shopping you know and I
remember the crying and the arguments
about it and that was in the 70s and
then you know she eventually got money
and it was okay but her stepping out of
her role was very threatening to him all
thanks long um anyone else besides
engine everything is crystal clear what
I'm saying anybody want to share that
what I've said has been helpful but
James has just raised his hand so if
James you want to chat that would be
great maybe I happened to space out at
the moment that you mention it
okay can you speak up a little bit James
a little bit better but still not that
how are you how's everyone else hearing
them yeah it's too good it's it's very
low you know what I will save my quest
for another time let's get it's gonna
take too long to figure this out
well you I just heard you fairly well
now okay here I go so the question is
about like as you're talking about these
different sort of states or levels of
consciousness moving from traditional
into modern sort of role role based
thinking into something more around
emotions and individuality I reflected
myself that I can see how I am
predominantly in one state of being but
these other states of being still do
express themselves in different ways so
I think I want to get maybe a
clarification on whether or not you're
talking about a progression that's like
once you're up you're up or that we you
know at any given point are always a
moving expression of all the states that
have come before us as well
that's like the number-one question
plaguing developmental theory and
whether it's a hierarchical development
and people are making all sorts of
models up to try and explain how it is
we can apparently move or digress to
lower stages of development and and how
does that make sense and what I've come
to see
so people have talked about like a
center of gravity where you're kind of
in one stage but you've got pieces below
you and pieces above you and that kind
of works I've actually started to
believe that it's not so much
hierarchical as contextual that a child
being born into a postmodern stage of
development is having huge demands made
on them on how to see the world and that
they will start embodying a postmodern
rhetoric and persona even if they
haven't individuated fully and so
there's you know it's very contextual
when they can have that sensitivity to
others but when it comes to knowing who
they are and what they're doing that
they're like they have no idea and one
of the things about doing it in a
hierarchy is that there is better
preparation like one of the insights
I've had about
modernism is it's it's not just a cheap
meant oriented it's extremely humbling
you know anyone who's individuated or
got to explore who they are and what
they can do in the world how many of you
have achieved all of the potential that
you felt you had put up your hands if
you've achieved all of the potential of
your individuation it's extremely
humbling it's not you know it's like
we're not all world-class athletes we're
not all the greatest musicians were not
all going to become millionaires and so
that humbling process of modernity
really sets the stage for a true
understanding of post-modernism where
you get that everybody is sort of
suffering and everybody's doing the best
they can and that's a true embrace of
other people the world you've been
humbled enough to not be believed you
know what's going on and for people who
haven't gone through that I think that's
part of why we get the social justice
warriors because they're more at a
traditional rules roles black and white
thinking kind of thing and they go with
that more essential component into the
postmodern rhetoric but they still parse
it at this lower stage so you know it
really is I think they're like different
ways of handling different situations
right if you get drawn into a conflict
with somebody you're likely either gonna
go traditional rules and roles this is
how you should act or you're gonna get
angry and try and intimidate them into
you know being a certain way and then
when you're not in conflict you can kind
of be in an intellectual position so we
kind of move up and down the
developmental stages depending on the
development and some of us are well that
gets a little bit too complicated but
it's very much more contextual than
developmental but we kind of have to do
all the stages anyway because they all
have their place in different situations
postmodern embrace of everything in the
midst of really gross violence doesn't
do that well sometimes you have to you
know address somebody trying to shoot
you with survival instincts not speech
right so that's
different sort of story and then and
maybe triggering people and I wish we
could get into it but but but not so
let's go back to processing emotions so
one of the things that I have come to
appreciate is most of us don't achieve
what we hope to achieve because we've
got something interfering with our
actual izing ourselves so how many
people here find themselves knowing they
should do something but they for some
reason don't do that okay now thank you
for being honest and thank you for
putting up your hands the question is
what do you do about that now most
people will try and rationally override
and convince themselves and use
willpower what I've found is that most
of us have an emotional impression in
our system that we've been carrying
around for a while which gets stimulated
into existence at the exact wrong times
and interferes with us taking that step
so let's suppose I'm an entrepreneur and
I have this great product and I've done
all of this work and I've done you know
I can sit at home on the computer do all
of this stuff and now it comes to the
point where I have to start phoning
people and selling them on the idea but
I find I never quite get around to that
phone call I can go see all the coaches
and get all the advice on how to do it
how to set it up and how to do so many
cold calls a day but what I find is that
that person's being triggered by the
phone call and they've got an
unconscious emotional fear you know of
what's going to happen so let's suppose
a person has a deep feeling of
insignificance they find that every time
they go to make a phone call they start
thinking old
person doesn't want to talk to me I'm
gonna interrupt that person they're too
important to want to talk to me right or
maybe they got a feeling of helplessness
and it's like oh it doesn't no matter
what I do I'm never gonna get people to
like you know go with this product and
and it's it's an unconscious thing
they're not saying this out loud they're
feeling it and they collapse away from
their goals and I'm using
entrepreneurialship because I've worked
with entrepreneurs and it's amazing when
you do this work how suddenly you can
move through those barriers and and I
think in many ways entrepreneurialship
is an awesome spiritual practice because
it forces you to face all of your
unresolved issues because there's so
many steps involved in becoming a
successful entrepreneur that everybody's
issues will be triggered at some point
just like a good relationship will
trigger
everybody's unresolved issues at some
point that's why relationships are so
difficult they sensitize us so now I've
been talking about impressions I'm gonna
give you a phrase and this is what I
would consider like a pith teaching a
pith teaching means that it's like the
the sutras or pith teachings the more
you understand about the teachings and
you go back and read the same sutras the
more you'll get from those sutras or
those teachings so here's a pissed
teaching from the bio motive framework
and it's funny I've gone to that window
twice and it didn't come so any intense
interpersonal encounter that's not fully
experienced and expressed
will become part of your sense of self
or worldview instead of something that
happened to you now
take take a few seconds to contemplate
that any intense interpersonal encounter
that isn't fully experienced and
expressed will become part of your sense
of self or worldview
instead of something that happened to
you so for example I worked with
somebody who had OCD this is an extreme
it doesn't have to show up as OCD and
she was working in an institution where
perfectionism was reinforced doing
things properly and rigorously and so
her OCD was helpful but then it started
getting in the way so she comes for
therapy and we are going through her
history trying to find the feelings that
were going on between her you know
underneath her need for perfection and
we came across a memory where she was in
kindergarten and she had this half hour
to draw a picture and she really loved
her kindergarten teachers so she drew a
picture of the kindergarten teacher and
her together and just put her whole
heart into it and then at the end of the
half hour you know art period she went
up to the teacher and just like meekly
gave it to the teacher like with her
whole heart like they trying to express
this deep sense of connection and the
teacher looked at it and she was busy
she huh you can do better than that
and gave it back to her and it just
devastated her you can do better than
that meanwhile she put her entire heart
into making this beautiful picture and
the impression was of inadequacy
she felt in adequate and she didn't go
home and cry about it where her parents
could hold her and have her talk about
the experience and let her know that it
was a beautiful picture and maybe say
that the teacher was just busy but where
she'd feel loved and accepted for where
she was she didn't do that she didn't
fully experience and express it so it
became part of her sense of self and
world view so that generalized into my
trying my best is not enough
I am inadequate and even my best isn't
good enough so if your best isn't good
enough you do a hundred and ten percent
one hundred and twenty percent you you
do it beyond your best she became
perfectionistic once she found that and
cried about it and talked about how
devastating it was as a child to do that
guess what happened she lost a whole lot
of the energy that was driving her
perfectionism and it took one or two
other examples of those kinds of things
because we tend to relive the same
experiences
once we've got an impression in but
eventually she be sensually lost her OCD
yes and that's an example now it's
become an event that happened to her
okay now there's a book called unlocking
the emotional brain that's also
discovered the same process from a dairy
very different perspective I've been
doing this for 20 plus years and it's
nice to have convergence and validity in
some research saying that this is what
people are doing to rewire the emotional
system so impressions somebody asked me
in group the other day who'd done a lot
of meditation when I think about
clearing my emotional system it feels
like a lifetime of work that I can't
believe it could ever just be clear and
the nice thing about
this work is that what I found with my
nine core feelings is if they're just
nine of them literally over three years
of clinical practice and me doing again
lens focusing process and asking
bringing people to tears over and over
and asking what's the core of your
feeling what's the the word that
vibrates with the deepest level of pain
in you and they say this word after five
six ten different words this is the word
that deeply resonates I wrote the word
down and you know a hundred clients
later or two hundred whatever it was
over the three years I had nine words
just astounding nine words at the core
of all of our pain and suffering and
that's why I believe that this is like
the perceptual apparatus of our
emotional brain for perceiving our
relational status and so as a child
you've probably taken in core
impressions that have affected how you
feel about yourself and your
relationship to the world so we're gonna
do an exercise now that I call the core
feelings psychograph and what this is is
an opportunity to just tune into your
world I'm gonna have you say a phrase
out loud and then you're going to rank
how much reverberation in your body you
get from it on a scale of zero to ten
ten means you're almost in tears or
you're crying or you would be crying if
it was a better social situation to do
that in zero means no resonance at all
so this is a psychograph if the more
open and vulnerable you can be okay the
more kind of signal there will be to
noise we've got all sorts of repressive
mechanisms that keep us from feeling
things so even if you've got that you
can get a sense even if they only go to
four or five you'll see the relative
weighting and that will give you an idea
of where your issues are and how you
might be distorting the world anyone
have any questions about
what we're going to do before we do it
or any clarification probably better for
what I've talked about
so the way I parse the world
interpersonal feelings like rejected
abused dismissed create core feelings
very people react very differently to
being rejected
some people feel worthless some people
feel insignificant some people feel
helpless etc then causes the emotion so
it's a very simple linear system
feelings cause emotions interpersonal
feelings
Express the dynamics between two people
core feelings are about how I feel about
myself and my relational status to the
world cause emotions this psychograph is
going to get a sense of what's embedded
in your system you can do this paper
also in a situation if you've had a
fight with your spouse or something
happen at work or with a good friend
right the situation down go through the
situation find the feelings and ideally
it'll bring you to tears and once you've
done that enough you'll find a pattern
okay so we're gonna open up here's
here's the link it's in the chat room if
you press on tinyurl.com slash BEF core
it's gonna open up a Google document now
this document it'll ask for your email
address that gets put in my database so
you're gonna be registered on my website
if you don't want that you can
unsubscribe but this is a way of sending
you the summary PDF afterwards I wrote
the code in here in Java or in Google
script to take all your information and
create a PDF and send it to you so that
you can look at your psychograph and
take your record you can do this over
time now doing it on the computer is a
little distance it's easy to be
intellectual so even if you don't get
the emotional crying you'll get the
insights you'll see kind of what your
wiring is so is everyone opening up and
it's working okay
okay so I'm going to open that up as
well and I'm going to do something a
little differently this time which is so
you can put your email an alias you you
can skip out through what you're upset
about
and when you say briefly describe the
situation causing your distress just say
this is a psycho graph of my life okay
so you know it's not situational and
then just check out how you're feeling
right now just as an emotional being and
see how much sort of emotional energy
there is you know I don't have it set up
for positive or negative but if you've
got any negative emotional energy just
that you kind of live with on a day to
day basis just rate how big it feels in
this context okay now I am then going to
say have you repeat the words so two
please don't go ahead okay of yourself
or of me because I want to specifically
give you a certain type of experience
and I'm going to do it a little bit
differently than the form so the first
thing I want you to do is close your
eyes take a few breaths and I want you
to say out loud with a kind of curiosity
I feel alone
I feel alone and depending on the state
of your emotional system you'll get some
resonance
you can try variations like I'm all
alone in the world I'm all alone I feel
alone and just get a sense if if if that
phrase makes you want to cry then put it
in if there's just moderate activation
put a fine now staying in that space so
open your eyes enough to answer you know
the respond to the question
but also I'm going to read a definition
out to you and I want you to see if that
brings it changes the amount of kind of
activation sometimes our emotional
systems don't recognize the words but
they can kind of relate more to the
scenario so hanging out with I feel
alone alone having no sense of
connection or commonality with anyone
around you one can be in close physical
proximity to people even been engaging
in small talk at a crowded party or
social gathering and still feel very
alone in the world
lonesome solitaire and isolation are
close cousins in the interpersonal world
watching all the people huddled together
an apparently deep meaningful
conversation laughing and engaged with
each other made me feel very alone in
the world as I shuffled from one group
to another looking for some sense of
connection so just see how your
emotional system resonated with those
the definition in that example and if
you got more resonance once you kind of
started relating to those words then
just increase your score
now we're going to move on to the next
one
want you to say I feel inadequate
I feel inadequate sometimes the words I
am inadequate might resonate more so try
that I am inadequate
and give yourself an
number between 0 and 10 for how much
that resonates lacking in capacity or
skill to achieve the goal or overcome
the challenge or obtain the outcome you
desire
it's something you might have the
potential to achieve if you work at it
but you're not presently capable feeling
deficient insufficient or lacking are
its cousins and the interpersonal world
I felt inadequate as I wrestled with the
heavy box and it thumped on the floor
not having been able to lift it high
enough to place it on the counter
I felt inadequate as I tried to express
my feelings to my partner and it just
kept going wrong and I couldn't do any
better and just if you've got an
increase from that and mark it up a
little bit higher we're going to go on
to the next one
I feel insignificant
I feel insignificant I am insignificant
now if you're crying I hope it's okay
this is kind of an exploration as to
what's going on with your emotional
system if it's overwhelming then I would
encourage you after this to reach out
for support and talk to somebody don't
handle this on your own if you can if
you have options and if you are
overwhelmed and don't have anyone to
reach out to then maybe send an email to
me you know and I can turn you towards
some support but hopefully there is
support for you somewhere the other
thing if you find yourself getting tired
or yawning you know or bored and wanting
to leave that's might tell you something
about your relationship to your emotions
some people when their emotional system
gets activated they close down they shut
down they get tired it's the kind of
stress induced narcolepsy and I've
actually had people fall asleep during
therapy as I got through emotional
systems activated because they're just
an automatic I shut down so I feel
insignificant to feel small and
unimportant like you don't register in
another person's world lacking position
or influence on matter is important to
you it's close cousins are small
invisible unimportant and overlooked
I felt small and insignificant as my
boss congratulated a colleague who got
the position I had applied for he hadn't
even bothered talking to me first before
making the announcement so we're gonna
pause there we've done three of the nine
and I'd like you to just reflect if you
don't mind on how this is going for you
what's happening if you don't mind
sharing any experiences insights or
feelings just can people put up their
hand or even just you know unmute
themselves in chat is anyone want to
share ideally someone who hasn't spoken
yet but just a few minute of questions
should we stop recording right now I
[Music]
guess if I'm okay with recording if we I
guess we don't need the recording yeah
so let's I guess the only thing is if
could you pause it when we do this once
and start it up yeah start it when I
talk yeah let's do that
oh you lost I feel lost that means you
don't have a vision I feel lost unable
to find your way not knowing which
direction to go to obtains one's goal
well it's easy to relate to feeling lost
in terms of the physical location
it's most often experienced in modern
times as being without a vision or
having a vision and no idea how to
achieve it or having no idea how to make
sense of what's going on John felt quite
lost
after receiving notice he was not
accepted into the military academy
he'd organised his whole life around
becoming a fighter pilot and had no idea
what to do with himself now
so mark in the kind of resonance you
have there we're gonna go on to I feel
helpless
I feel hopeless feel helpless
mark what you got there helpless the
inability to affect change in the area
you want like feeling trapped in a job
you hate but can't afford to quit having
someone hold you down and you can't move
no matter how hard you try the words
powerless weak and impotent are close
cousins in the interpersonal world
jennifer remembers feeling very helpless
as a four year old listening to her
mother and father fight yelling and
screaming at each other
all she wanted was for them to stop but
no amount of yelling screaming or crying
on her part seemed to make any
difference I feel helpless
moving on to worthless I feel worthless
I feel worthless this can be very
threatening for people if you're giving
yourself a zero without even thinking
about it just maybe be open to wondering
if maybe that's in there and you're
hiding from it it's not necessarily
always true but it often does happen
feeling like you have no worth no value
to anyone or anything
feeling like you bring nothing
beneficial to the world or the people
around you some people relate more to
the interpersonal feeling of being
broken at a fundamental level like they
were born with a deficit that makes them
very different from other human beings I
feel
worthless John was getting so much
negative feedback about his fixation
with his smartphone that he was
beginning to think there was something
wrong with him
he realized he was starting to feel like
a worthless human being who would never
amount to anything
I feel worthless I feel an emptiness I
feel an emptiness inside now when you're
doing it situationally you say I feel a
loss now when you've had a loss for a
long time a feeling of loss that doesn't
resolve itself over time will become a
feeling of emptiness a hole in your
heart where the positive feeling once
lived
so living with a loss for a long time
ends up becoming a feeling of emptiness
gonna move on I feel like a bad person I
feel like a bad person the person feels
bad when they violated one no more rules
or norms associated with the vision of
their group family or tribe or one that
they've come to hold as their own while
experiencing any negative feeling state
could be described as feeling bad
this feeling is always feeling bad
something like I'm a bad person a bad
daughter bad son a bad wife being
ostracized and shunned our interpersonal
cousins of this feeling and are very
important to maintaining adherence to
the collective values of the group
Jeremy felt bad that his preoccupation
with the girl in the stand caused him to
miss the pass and allow the other team
to score Samantha felt
be bad about herself that she screamed
at her children that she spent her whole
life wanting to be a better mother than
hers had been
the last core feeling is hopeless
I feel hopeless so say that Oh remember
it's important to say the words out loud
I feel hopeless I feel hopeless the
feeling of hopelessness arises when you
feel the negative state you're in it's
never going to change
Victoria felt hopeless of utter exams
she'd been studying for weeks and every
time she took a practice test her grades
did not improve
George felt hopeless no matter how many
times he called his girlfriend to
apologize all he received were harsh
words and rejection he cried as he
accepted his loan list as alumnus and
realized he would never feel her warm
embrace again it was hopeless I'm just
catching the comment on the chat about
but the tone of my voice and yes I am
intentionally using tone to indo induce
states that's kind of what we're here
for and if my tone can trigger you
awesome it means you probably have
something going on yeah this isn't the
thing about the emotional system is that
it's not rational okay it came before
the intellect it evolved before the
intellect it's an irrational process by
definition but it's lawful you know
we're discovering the laws of the
emotional system so that we can work
with it and tone an interpersonal
context make a big difference than just
approaching it from an intellectual
point of view so we've had quite a
journey here I hope you can pleat the
form and hit return you'll get put on
the mailing list you'll get the PDF and
let's just take a few minutes to share
what was this experience like for you
and let's just kind of do popcorn you
don't have to put your hands up okay
just what was this like you've been
coming to these stoic sessions for a
while you've got different framework
I noticed I listen to Bonita Roy's frame
on emotions and it's really interesting
her 9 by 3 by 3 grid of you know
emotions this is very different this is
a very different approach to emotions
and it differentiates feelings where she
was differentiating effects and things
so what's your what's your take on this
from both an emotional and an
intellectual point of view how is this
landing guys give me give me some
feedback
and girls I don't cry I hope you know
I'm using the word generically
genderless Li maybe gray can chat do you
mind if I call on you
sorry feedback there um yeah I noticed
that the the three feelings that I rated
the highest were the feeling lost and
feeling alone and feeling an emptiness
and it was interesting like writing
those in that question at the bottom
where you like say which ones you rated
highest made me realize oh that's all of
the things that I feel challenged at the
stoah on like like I feel alone but then
here I'm reaching out to people even
when that kind of feels triggering and I
like have to confront my issues with
distrust and stuff like that and I I
feel really alone and then I come here
and people express things to me that
make me feel so much belonging and I'm
like wow that's really new I don't know
how to even really interpret that
sometimes and then yeah I feel really
lost and I don't know what I'm gonna do
I'm like really uncertain about my life
path and then everybody here feels like
very like-minded and gives me really
powerful ideas that resonate with me and
I don't know how they're going to like
fit together into a picture of my future
but I get such a like strong like
positive like hunch that I'm like on the
right track by being here so it was kind
of interesting to me that it just so
clarified for me that I'm like actually
kind of responsive to these core
feelings that are alive in me beautiful
and you're actually bringing us to
another level which is you have the
opportunity to take in positive feelings
of connection and caring every one of
these negative core feelings has a
corresponding positive one that we're
often exposed to but we don't take in
the impression because our emotional
systems shut down and by finding the
feelings and feeling beliefs we can open
them up and take in the impressions and
it'll upgrade the system right but you
have to feel the negative feelings for
it to to meet reality and realize that
it's not three or five years or ten
years old anymore
and it's living in a new world any thank
you thank you so much for for braving
your loneliness and your insecurities
and you know embracing the group and
letting us kind of love you collectively
you know appreciate appreciate your
contributions anyone else like to share
just turn your mic on and say something
Andrew I I'm very aware of how exhausted
I am like I'm very and and just enough
exhaustion to just even talk to like
even talk to you right now but I feel
that like just like I want to go take a
nap what I've done yet so there's two
things going on one is because we've
closed their emotional systems down when
we get the energy moving it's meeting a
lot of friction so if you get activated
to an eight but you're only expressive
to you've got six units of tension in
your system that's one reason you get
exhausted from doing this work and the
other is if we've done this long enough
we've learned to close down to shut down
this is like how depression works it you
get activated you don't process it it's
too dangerous to stay activated because
it's not going anywhere so you literally
shut down and go to sleep until the
activation passes but then you get up
again and you get stimulated and you
don't express it and your system has a
shutoff valve right so you have to learn
to unlearn that process and make it okay
to have feelings and emotions but it
makes sense that you've been doing this
because you haven't been given the tools
for the aliveness that you do have you
didn't shut your emotional systems down
well enough like we did in the 60s you
know and so you know now this is what I
feel this or something like this is
necessary to complete the postmodern
move if you don't
articulate your feelings and emotions at
this level you'll never really
understand and embrace feelings at the
level you need to to have the depth of
communication and relationship you're
looking for with yourself and others
it's 431 I'll take one more comment if
someone wants to share something and if
not yeah Nathan so I found out about
your framework from listening to the
emerge podcast and this was quite
recently but I wasn't I didn't have the
list of the nine core feelings so it was
very interesting for me going through
this exercise with you and I actually
found sorry to back up one more I played
around with this with myself seeing what
kind of core feelings I found and I had
named some feelings and I actually found
them here on this this list that you
shared awesome what one other thing I
was I really felt a strong emotional
reaction to quite a lot of them and I'm
just I'm like I think like you know I
like seven six or seven of them I'm up
around nine or ten I'm like and I'm
curious if they're but almost some of
them kind of seem to live in the same
place like you know worthless hopeless
and a bad person that all kind of drew
me to like a course maybe a core feeling
that's not to talk to your language but
yeah when I was finding these core
feelings I had hard time differentiating
some of them like hopeless and helpless
felt the same to me
and eventually I realized hopeless was a
temporal component of being stuck in a
feeling and helpless was its own unique
feeling that I could feel hopeless about
my in significance or hopeless about my
worthlessness but originally hopeless
and helpless felt the same the other
thing is developmentally
were programmed to to fuse some of them
so if I'm feeling inadequate at a modern
level
I'll also feel worthless because my
value at modern is based on what I can
do so if I can't do much then I am
worthless it's not to postmodern that
you get intrinsic worth and value for
just being you so you can see how
different developmental levels don't
have this just these distinctions they
literally are if you are inadequate or
helpless you are worthless and so we
have to like work to extract those out
in this new modern postmodern world so
I'm actually supposed to be golfing in
in an hour and a bit and I've got an
hour and a bit of a drive so this has
been wonderful
I hope that you continue checking out
this work and I hope this has helped you
on your journeys and if you want to give
me feedback you can always send me
something at info and byway motive
framework com I'd love to hear from you
and you know check out our website we've
got a variety of programs and online
sessions that you can join and and
resources that we're putting together
and you know I'm a full time clinician
and I'm trying to do this in my spare
time and the more income I get from my
online stuff the more it frees up to do
this kind of work and eventually to get
a book written so that you guys can just
sit down by a fireplace and read this
stuff and digest everything that's in my
head without having to talk to me even
though this is a wonderful way to do it
it's hard to reach a million or two
million people this way so thank you so
much for your for having me and thank
you all and I hope you all the best and
thank you for being such a wonderful
audience and maybe I'll see you on the
stoah another time thank you so much
Doug for coming today
it was a treat I think everyone thought
that was a treat here and yeah do
support Doug and hopefully he can have
more time to come on the store and then
work through our here so just
upcoming announcements of a couple of
events radio I'm bye bye Doug take care
radio would you like to talk about
Socratic speed-dating is coming up later
today thank you
yes so at 7:00 p.m. Eastern time we'll
be doing another round of Socratic
speed-dating so it'll be an opportunity
to meet all these beautiful faces that
you see in these new rooms have
conversation and ask questions and bond
with people in the stoic community so I
would love to see all of you there so
yeah and that's at 7:00 p.m. Eastern
time so just a little bit now and the
Socratic speed-dating stir like the
heart of the snowiest where all the cool
kids come and ask each other all the
juicy and edgy questions
Travis man he has a new event that's
coming to the wisdom gym Charlie's like
to talk about it yeah thanks Pierre so
my event is called breaking the frame
and it's a process a relational process
where we walk through examining our
worldviews and finding ways that we can
navigate through different world views
and maybe identify and uncover some of
the worldviews that we feel stuck in and
help each other out to process through
those and enhance our cognitive
flexibility beautiful Thank You Travis
and it hasn't been on the website yet on
June 17th at 3:00 p.m. Eastern Time all
the post rats love this we got James
cars from finite and infinite games
booked so if you don't know who he is
kind of like everyone loves them so yeah
that'd be awesome is gonna be called the
playing the infinite game in the met
during the meadow crisis so that should
be a really fun jam hopefully it works
out if I know there's a lot of intense
emotions we expressed experience today
you can go to the game be coffee house
and some closing this one down so if you
want to go jam with each other kind of
process together you can go there
yeah that being said thanks so much
everyone